I've been working on issues of poverty for more than 20 years,
لقد عملت في قضايا الفقر لأكثر من 20 عاماً،
and so it's ironic that the problem that and question that I most grapple with
ومن المفارقات أن المشكلة والسؤال الذي لابد من مواجهته
is how you actually define poverty. What does it mean?
هو كيف نعرّف الفقر حقيقةً. ماذا يعني الفقر؟
So often, we look at dollar terms --
لذاً دائماً، نحن نأخذ بقيمة الدولار--
people making less than a dollar or two or three a day.
الناس الذين يكسبون أقل من دولار أو أثنين أو ثلاثة يومياً.
And yet the complexity of poverty really has to look at
ومع تعقيد الفقر ما زلنا ننظر
income as only one variable.
في الدخل كالعامل الوحيد فقط.
Because really, it's a condition about choice,
لأنه في الواقع، أنه شرط حول الإختيار،
and the lack of freedom.
ونقصان الحرية.
And I had an experience that really deepened and elucidated for me
ولدي تجربة عمّقت حقاً وشرحت لي
the understanding that I have.
الفهم الذي توصلت إليه.
It was in Kenya, and I want to share it with you.
لقد كان في كينيا، وأردت تقاسمها معكم.
I was with my friend Susan Meiselas, the photographer,
كنت مع صديقتي سوسان مايسالاس، المصوّرة،
in the Mathare Valley slums.
وفي أحياء وادي ماثاري.
Now, Mathare Valley is one of the oldest slums in Africa.
الآن، وادي ماثاري أحد أقدم الأحياء الفقيرة في أفريقيا.
It's about three miles out of Nairobi,
يبعد حوالي ثلاثة أميال عن نيروبي،
and it's a mile long and about two-tenths of a mile wide,
ويبلغ طوله ميلاً وعرضه حوالي أثنين أعشار الميل،
where over half a million people
حيث ما يزيد على نصف مليون شخص
live crammed in these little tin shacks,
يعيشون في هذه الأكواخ المكتظة،
generation after generation, renting them,
جيلاً بعد جيل، يستأجرونها،
often eight or 10 people to a room.
عادةً ثمانية الى عشرة أشخاص في الغرفة.
And it's known for prostitution, violence, drugs:
وأنها معروفة بالبغاء، العنف، المخدرات.
a hard place to grow up.
مكان قاسي للعيش فيه.
And when we were walking through the narrow alleys,
وبينما كنا نتمشى عبر الأزقة الضيقة،
it was literally impossible not to step in the
لقد كان من المستحيل حرفياً تجنب الخطو في
raw sewage and the garbage alongside the little homes.
مياة المجاري والقمامة بجانب البيوت الصغيرة.
But at the same time it was also
لكن في نفس الوقت كان أيضاً
impossible not to see the human vitality,
مستحيلاً عدم رؤية حيوية الإنسان،
the aspiration and the ambition of the people who live there:
والتطلع والطموح للناس الذين يعيشون هناك.
women washing their babies, washing their clothes, hanging them out to dry.
النساء يغسلن أطفالهن، يغسلن ملابسهن، ينشرونها لتجف.
I met this woman, Mama Rose,
إلتقيت مع هذه المرأة، الأم روس،
who has rented that little tin shack for 32 years,
التي إستأجرت ذلك الكوخ الضيق لمدة 32 عاماً،
where she lives with her seven children.
حيث تعيش مع أطفالها السبعة.
Four sleep in one twin bed,
ينام أربعة في سرير مزدوج،
and three sleep on the mud and linoleum floor.
وينام ثلاثة في أرضية من الطين ومشمع.
And she keeps them all in school by selling water from that kiosk,
وترسلهم جميعاً الى المدرسة ببيع الماء من ذلك الكشك،
and from selling soap and bread from the little store inside.
وعبر بيع الصابون والخبز من داخل المتجر الصغير.
It was also the day after the inauguration,
ولقد كان يوماً بعد حفل التنصيب،
and I was reminded how Mathare is still connected to the globe.
وأتذكر كيف أن ماثار ما تزال متواصلة مع العالم.
And I would see kids on the street corners,
وأرى الأطفال في نواصي الشوارع،
and they'd say "Obama, he's our brother!"
ويقولون " أوباما، أنه أخونا!"
And I'd say "Well, Obama's my brother, so that makes you my brother too."
وأنا أقول " حسناً، أوباما أخي، وذلك يجعلكم أخواني أيضاً."
And they would look quizzically, and then be like, "High five!"
ويقومون بالتساؤل، وبعد ذلك يبدون، " لنتصافح!"
And it was here that I met Jane.
ولقد كنت هنا وإلتقيت ب جين.
I was struck immediately by the kindness and the gentleness in her face,
أدهشني على الفور اللطف والوداعة في وجهها،
and I asked her to tell me her story.
وطلبت منها إخباري بقصتها.
She started off by telling me her dream. She said, "I had two.
لقد بدأت بإخباري عن حلمها. قالت، " لديّ أثنين من الأحلام.
My first dream was to be a doctor,
حلمي الأول كان أن أصبح طبيبة،
and the second was to marry a good man
والثاني كان أن أتزوج رجلاً طيباً
who would stay with me and my family,
الذي سيقف معي ومع أسرتي.
because my mother was a single mom,
لأن أمي كانت أم بلا زوج،
and couldn't afford to pay for school fees.
ولم أستطيع توفير مصاريف دراستي.
So I had to give up the first dream, and I focused on the second."
لذا توجّب عليّ ترك حلمي الأول، وركّزت على الثاني."
She got married when she was 18, had a baby right away.
لقد تزوجت عندما بلغت سن 18، وأنجبت طفلاً على طول.
And when she turned 20, found herself pregnant with a second child,
وعندما بلغت سن 20، وجدت نفسها حامل بالطفل الثاني،
her mom died and her husband left her -- married another woman.
توفيت والدتها وهجرها زوجها -- تزوج إمرأة أخرى.
So she was again in Mathare, with no income, no skill set, no money.
لذا فقد كانت مجدداً في ماثاري، بلا دخل مادي بلا مهارات، بلا مال.
And so she ultimately turned to prostitution.
لذا ففي نهاية المطاف إتجهت الى الدعارة.
It wasn't organized in the way we often think of it.
لم يكن الأمرر مخطط له بالصورة التي نعتقدها عادةً.
She would go into the city at night with about 20 girls,
كانت تذهب الى المدينة في الليل مع حوالي 20 فتاة،
look for work, and sometimes come back with a few shillings,
يبحثون عن عمل، وبعض الأحيان تعود بالقليل من الشيلنات (عملة كينيا)،
or sometimes with nothing.
وبعض الأحيان بلا شئ.
And she said, "You know, the poverty wasn't so bad. It was the humiliation
لقد قالت،" تعرفي، الفقر لم يكن شيئاً سيئاً. كان الإذلال
and the embarrassment of it all."
والحرج من كل ذلك. "
In 2001, her life changed.
في العام، تغيّرت حياتها.
She had a girlfriend who had heard about this organization, Jamii Bora,
كان لديها صديقة سمعت بهذه المنظمة، جامي بورا،
that would lend money to people no matter how poor you were,
التي تقرض المال الى الناس غض النظر عن مدى فقرهم،
as long as you provided a commensurate amount in savings.
طالما أنك توفر مبلغ يتناسب مع المدخرات.
And so she spent a year to save 50 dollars,
ولذا فقد قضت سنة لتوفير مبلغ 50 دولاراً،
and started borrowing, and over time she was able to buy a sewing machine.
وبدأت بالإقتراض، وعبر الزمن إستطاعت شراء ماكينة خياطة.
She started tailoring.
وبدأت بالتطريز.
And that turned into what she does now,
وذلك تحوّل الى ما تعمله الآن،
which is to go into the secondhand clothing markets,
وهو أن تذهب الى سوق الملابس المستعملة،
and for about three dollars and 25 cents she buys an old ball gown.
وبحوالي ثلاثة دولارات و 25 سنتاً تشتري كومة ملابس قديمة.
Some of them might be ones you gave.
بعضها ربما تكونوا قد تبرعتم بها أنتم.
And she repurposes them with frills and ribbons,
وتقوم بإعادة تصميمها بالرتوش والأشرطة،
and makes these frothy confections that she sells to women
وتصنع هذه الحلويات المزبدة التي تبيعها الى النساء
for their daughter's Sweet 16 or first Holy Communion --
لبناتهن في أعمار ال 16 أو للقربان المقدس --
those milestones in a life that people want to celebrate
تلك المعالم البارزة في حياة الناس الذين يرغبون بالإحتفال
all along the economic spectrum.
على امتداد الطيف الاقتصادي.
And she does really good business. In fact, I watched her
وهي تقوم بعمل جيد حقاً. في الواقع، لقد شاهدتها
walk through the streets hawking. And before you knew it,
تبيع في الشوارع متجولة. وقبل أن تعرفها،
there was a crowd of women around her, buying these dresses.
كان هناك إزدحام نسائي حولها، يشترون هذه الثياب.
And I reflected, as I was watching her sell the dresses,
ولقد تأملت، بينما كنت أشاهدها تبيع الثياب،
and also the jewelry that she makes,
وأيضاً الحلية التي تصنعها.
that now Jane makes more than four dollars a day.
أن جين دخلها أكثر من أربعة دولارات يومياً.
And by many definitions she is no longer poor.
وبالعديد من التعريفات لم تعد فقيرة.
But she still lives in Mathare Valley.
لكنها ما تزال تعيش في وادي ماثاري.
And so she can't move out.
ولا تستطيع الإنتقال منه.
She lives with all of that insecurity,
تعيش مع إنعدام الأمن،
and in fact, in January, during the ethnic riots,
وفي الواقع، في يناير، أثناء أعمال العنف العرقية،
she was chased from her home and had to find a new shack
تم مطاردتها من بيتها وتوجّب عليها إيجاد كوخ جديد
in which she would live.
الذي ستعيش فيه.
Jamii Bora understands that and understands
جامي بورا تفهم ذلك. وتفهم
that when we're talking about poverty,
أنه عندما نتحدث عن الفقر،
we've got to look at people all along the economic spectrum.
علينا أن ننظر إلى كافة الناس على امتداد الطيف الاقتصادي.
And so with patient capital from Acumen and other organizations,
ولذا فمع رأس المال الصبور من أكيومن ومنظمات أخرى،
loans and investments that will go the long term with them,
القروض والإستثمارات التي تمضي على المدى الطويل معهم،
they built a low-cost housing development,
تقوم بصنع تنمية ببناء مساكن منخفضة التكلفة،
about an hour outside Nairobi central.
على بعد حوالي الساعة خارج وسط نيروبي.
And they designed it from the perspective of
وأنها مصممة انها من وجهة نظر
customers like Jane herself,
العملاء مثل جين نفسها،
insisting on responsibility and accountability.
وتصر على المسؤولية والمساءلة.
So she has to give 10 percent of the mortgage --
لذا فعليها أن تعطي 10 في المئة من التمويل العقاري--
of the total value, or about 400 dollars in savings.
للقيمة الكلية، أو حوالي 400 دولاراً من المدخرات.
And then they match her mortgage to what she paid in rent for her little shanty.
وبعد ذلك يقومون بمقارنة رهنها مع ما دفعته في الإيجار لبيتها من الصفيح.
And in the next couple of weeks, she's going to be
وفي الأسابيع القليلة القادمة، ستكون
among the first 200 families to move into this development.
بين أول 200 أسرة تتنقل داخل هذا التطوير.
When I asked her if she feared anything,
عندما سألتها إذا كانت تخشى أي شئ،
or whether she would miss anything from Mathare,
أو سواء كانت ستفتقد أي شئ من ماثاري،
she said, "What would I fear
قالت،" ما سأخشاه
that I haven't confronted already?
قد تم مواجهتي به بالفعل؟
I'm HIV positive. I've dealt with it all."
أنا أحمل فيروس الإيدز. لقد تعايشت مع كل شئ."
And she said, "What would I miss?
وقالت، ماذا سأفتقد؟
You think I will miss the violence or the drugs? The lack of privacy?
تعتقدين أنني سأفتقد العنف والمخدرات؟ إنعدام الخصوصية؟
Do you think I'll miss not knowing if my children are going to come home
هل تعتقدين أنني سأفتقد عدم معرفة إذا ما كان أطفالي سيعودوا الى المنزل
at the end of the day?" She said "If you gave me 10 minutes
في نهاية اليوم؟ وتقول " إذا أعطيتني 10 دقائق
my bags would be packed."
ستكون حقائبي جاهزة للمغادرة."
I said, "Well what about your dreams?"
قلت لها، " حسناً ماذا عن أحلامك؟"
And she said, "Well, you know,
وردت، " حسناً، تعلمين،
my dreams don't look exactly like I thought they would when I was a little girl.
إن أحلامي لا تبدو تماماً كما كنت أفكر بها عندما كنت طفلة صغيرة.؟
But if I think about it, I thought I wanted a husband,
لكن إذا فكرت بها، أعتقدت أنني أريد زوجاً،
but what I really wanted was a family
لكن ما أردته بالفعل كان الأسرة المُحبة
that was loving. And I fiercely love my children, and they love me back."
وأنا أحب أطفالي بشراسة، ويبادلوني الحب."
She said, "I thought that I wanted to be a doctor,
وقالت، " أعتقدت أنني أريد أن أصبح طبيبة،
but what I really wanted to be was somebody
لكن ما أردته بالفعل هو شخص ما
who served and healed and cured.
خدوم ويعافي ويشفي.
And so I feel so blessed with everything that I have,
ولذا أشعر بالبركة في كل شئ لدي،
that two days a week I go and I counsel HIV patients.
وأنني أذهب كل أسبوعين للإستشارة الخاصة بمرضى الإيدز.
And I say, 'Look at me. You are not dead.
وأقول، "أنظر إليّ. أنا لست ميتة.
You are still alive. And if you are still alive you have to serve.'"
ما أزال على قيد الحياة. إذا كنت حية ينبغي عليك الخدمة."
And she said, "I'm not a doctor who gives out pills.
ولقد قالت، " أنا لست طبيبة تصرف الوصفات.
But maybe me, I give out something better
لكن ربما أنا، أعطي شيئاً أفضل
because I give them hope."
لأنني أعطيهم أمل."
And in the middle of this economic crisis,
وفي أثناء الأزمة الإقتصادية،
where so many of us are inclined to pull in
حيث يميل الكثيرون منا إلى الإنسحاب
with fear, I think we're well suited to
مع الخوف، أعتقد أننا مناسبين تماماً
take a cue from Jane and reach out,
لنحذو حذو جين وأن نعرف،
recognizing that being poor doesn't mean being ordinary.
بأنه إذا كنت فقيراً لا يعني أنك عادي.
Because when systems are broken,
لأنه عندما تنهار الأنظمة،
like the ones that we're seeing around the world,
مثل تلك التي نراها حول العالم،
it's an opportunity for invention and for innovation.
فأنها فرصة للإبتكار وللإختراع.
It's an opportunity to truly build a world
أنها فرصة حقيقية لبناء عالم
where we can extend services and products
حيث يمكننا توسيع الخدمات والمنتجات
to all human beings, so that they can
لكل البشرية، بحيث يستطيعون
make decisions and choices for themselves.
أخذ قرارات وخيارات لأنفسهم.
I truly believe it's where dignity starts.
أعتقد بصدق أن هناك حيث تبدأ الكرامة.
We owe it to the Janes of the world.
نحن مدينون لكل "جين" في العالم.
And just as important, we owe it to ourselves.
وبنفس القدر من الأهمية، نحن مدينون لأنفسنا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)